A Guide to the Virginia Geological Survey, Records, 1834-1903
Library of Virginia
- Series I: Correspondence of William B. Rogers, 1836-1903
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - George W. Boyd, Maysville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 2, 1839, George W. Boyd, Maysville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of Buckingham, Cumberland, and Prince Edward counties. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - James B. Rogers, Frankfort, to [William B. Rogers, University of Virginia], June 4 and 5, 1839, James B. Rogers, Frankfort, to [William B. Rogers, University of Virginia], giving him bad news of a broken down horse, bad weather, and a broken altitude thermometer; reporting on the geology of the Greenbrier River-Greenbrier Mountain area; discussing his plans to proceed toward New River; and mentioning his health. Attached is a section of the area described in the letter and a request for money and for a small pocket thermometer. 5 pp. with address leaf.
    - James B. Rogers, White Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 5, 1839, James B. Rogers, White Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his recent letter; answering questions posed about the geology of the mountains around Covington; commenting on Beard's Mountain and the new spring at White Sulphur Springs; asking for a new thermometer; and discussing the mail. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Columbus, [Ohio], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 6, 1839, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Columbus, [Ohio], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing Rogers that he had sent him a letter [on May 24] enclosing a testimonial from Professor Eaton, which he feared had miscarried, and asking if his presence on the survey was still desired. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Wythe Court House, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 8, [1839], I[srael] Slade, Wythe Court House, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letter of May 28; describing his suffering resulting from a piece of rock imbedding itself in his eye; and discussing the geology of Lick Mountain, New River, and Iron Mountain. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 10, 1839, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that the Board of Public Works had that day confirmed Rogers's appointment of Caleb Briggs as assistant geologist; discussing financial matters; and rendering an account of contingent expenses due Rogers. 1 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 10, 1839, George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the geology of Amherst County, especially in the vicinity of Buffalo Ridge, White's Gap, Cold Mountain, Mount Pleasant, and Long Mountain; mentioning various persons he encountered on his way; outlining his plans to travel through Bedford, Campbell, Charlotte, Franklin, and Pittsylvania counties to Halifax County; hoping Rogers can join him; and discussing financial matters. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 14 and 15, 1839, James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the area of Frankfort, the Great Levels, Culbertsons Creek, Brushy Ridge, Sinking Creek, and Greenbrier Mountain; including a section of the same area; including a section of the same area; and discussing the Blue Sulphur Springs. 4 pp.
    - George W. Boyd, Liberty, Bedford County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 17, 1839, George W. Boyd, Liberty, Bedford County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the affliction of his horse, Dragon, and how he treated it and listing the contents of two sample boxes. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Wythe C[ourt] House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 20, 1839, I[srael] Slade, Wythe C[ourt] House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, complaining that his trunk has been lost; discussing his problems with horses; mentioning his plans to examine Little Walkers Mountain; and describing the geology of the area around Walkers Creek, Burk's Garden, and Brushy Mountain. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Campbell Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 22, 1839, George W. Boyd, Campbell Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing minerals found in Beford and Campbell counties. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Charlotte Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 26, 1839, George W. Boyd, Charlotte Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of June 13; describing his plans to proceed to Danville, Leaksville, and back to Lynchburg to spend a few days drawing sections; and asking that his quarter's salary be sent to Lynchburg. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - James B. Rogers, Millers Locust Grove, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 27 and 28, 1839, James B. Rogers, Millers Locust Grove, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the lameness of his horse, Billy, and describing the geology of Muddy Creek Mountain, Meadow Mountain, Guinn's Spring, the falls of New River, and the Little and Big Sewells. 4 pp.
    - George W. Boyd, Charlotte Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 27, 1839, George W. Boyd, Charlotte Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of parts of Albemarle, Nelson, Buckingham, Cumberland, Amherst, Prince Edward, Bedford, Campbell, and Charlotte counties and describing what remained to be examined in those counties. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, Yellow Springs, Chester County, Pennsylvania, July 9, 1839, George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, Yellow Springs, Chester County, Pennsylvania, describing the geology of the areas around Leaksville, Smith River, White Oak Mountain, Pittsylvania Court House, Danville, and Campbell Court House. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[harles] B. Hayden, Woodstock, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, July 9, [1839], C[harles] B. Hayden, Woodstock, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, concerning his treatment of and recovery from a recent "digestive affection"; referring obscurely to the "Smoot affair," of which he took no "public notice;" and describing his plans to proceed to Strasburg, Martinsburg, and Winchester. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, August 11, 1839, George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that he hoped Rogers could join him before September 1 and mentioning that he had visited Bedford and Franklin counties and planned to go to Patrick and Henry counties next. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Pittsylvania Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 1, 1839, George W. Boyd, Pittsylvania Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the geology of Campbell, Bedford, Franklin, Pittsylvania, and Halifax counties; mentioning limestone used in Ross's new iron works and at the Rocky Mount furnace; commenting upon the proper stone to use as a hearthstone in an iron furnace; and mentioning the sections he had been drawing. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 3, 1839, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, regarding Rogers's trunk; describing coal beds along the Ohio River on the Virginia side; mentioning residents eager to render assistance to the geologists; and touching upon his health. 3 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Danville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 15, 1839, George W. Boyd, Danville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, briefly describing limestone found in Patrick and Henry counties; mentioning an iron furnace and forge on Goblintown Creek in Patrick County; and noting globular greenstone found near Danville. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Wellsburg [Wellsville], Ohio, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 17, 1839, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Wellsburg [Wellsville], Ohio, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing limestone and coal ground near Wheeling, Virginia, and speculating on the extent of these seams and discussing an iron furnace and mines formerly in operation above Steubenville in Virginia. 4 pp.
    - George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 22, 1839, George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging Rogers's letter of September 7; describing a curious, large piece of sandstone with depressions like those caused by horses hooves near White Oak Mountain in Pittsylvania county and mentioning his plans to go by way of Amherst and Nelson counties to the University. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Middletown, Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, October 14, 1839, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Middletown, Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of Virginia along the Ohio River; presenting a table showing coal and other minerals found at various levels in the "Pittsburg Coal Series" near Wheeling; and mentioning his financial problems. 4 pp.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, October 30, 1839, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing Rogers of his plans to proceed to Charlottesville because he has run out of money and discussing the problems of tracing the various "strata composing the Wheeling Series." 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, November 28, 1839, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the financial affairs of the survey and discussing the problems facing the General Assembly about to convene. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, December 7, 1839, George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, regretting his leaving his section drawings and notes with Rogers when he had the means of working on them in New York and returning them to Virginia and proposing a four to six week visit to the University to catalog fossils. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, to W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, n.p., December 13, 1839, William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, to W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, n.p., enclosing as much of the money demanded by Aikin as Rogers was able to procure and asking for a receipt; recalling his past liberality with Aikin in financial matters; reminding him that he was paid $200. more per year than any other assistant geologist; and stating that the amount and quality of work produced by Aikin was not worth the extra pay and the trouble he had caused Rogers. 2 pp., draft.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, December 19, 1839, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the financial affairs of the survey and predicting a great reduction of funds for the survey or its complete elimination as a result of economic conditions and the depleted state of the Treasury. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, December 26, 1839, George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, wishing him "many happy returns of the season"; noting that he had received no response from Rogers to his letter of December 7; informing him that he had almost accompanied a friend to Trinidad; and saying that he planned to spend part of the winter in Charleston and Savannah and hoped to stop by Charlottesville on his way there. 1 p. with address leaf.
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - E. C. Howard, Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, January 28, 1840, E. C. Howard, Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of January 23; referring to financial affairs; and telling him that James Brown, Jr., would have written Rogers himself if it were not for the press of business. 1 p. with address leaf. E. C. Howard was the second clerk in the Second Auditor's Office.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., University of Virginia, to William B. Rogers, Richmond, February 6, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., University of Virginia, to William B. Rogers, Richmond, describing specimens of limestones and including the amount of carb[olic?] acid found in each sample. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, March 19, 1840, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of March 16 and noting the deposit of funds to the credit of Rogers and Caleb Briggs, Jr.; wishing he would come to Richmond to settle his accounts for the year; and repeating what he had heard from members of the General Assembly: "that you will complete your duties during the year commencing 2d April next." 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, March 31, 1840, George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing Rogers that Henry D. Rogers's opinions of the Hudson River slates have been vindicated by New York geologists; presenting his plans to leave for Virginia on April 15 by way of Philadelphia, Baltimore, and Richmond; offering to take care of any business for Rogers that might need doing in those cities; and enclosing his account due April 1 (not found). 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 17, 1840, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letter of April 7; mentioning financial matters; informing him that the Board of Public Works had approved all of his plan of operation for the coming year except that part requesting an additional assistant; acknowledging receipt of James B. Roger's resignation and expressing his regrets; and expressing concern for his health. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Harrisonburg, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 19, [1840], I[srael] Slade, Harrisonburg, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the geology of Turk's Gap and Payne's Run and including rough pencil sketches of sections of the area described. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - Robert Mills, Washington, D.C., to [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, April 25, 1840, Robert Mills, Washington, D.C., to [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for copies of Rogers's reports or other information pertaining to the geology of Jackson's River, in particular around Warm Springs and Hot Springs, and commenting on the importance of the survey and the mineral wealth of Virginia. 2 pp. with address leaf. Robert Mills (August 12, 1781-March 3, 1855), architect and engineer, was at this time Architect of Public Buildings for the federal government.
    - I[srael] Slade, Luray, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 28, 1840, I[srael] Slade, Luray, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the mountainous area around Luray. 4 pp.
    - George W. Boyd, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 3, 1840, George W. Boyd, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology observed along the roads from Charlottesville to Richmond and mentioning repairs made to his buggy. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Cloverdale, to William Rogers, University of Virginia, May 5, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Cloverdale, to William Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning his baggage which had gone on the wrong stage and a $20 bank note which he had lost. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Culpeper Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 11, 1840, George W. Boyd, Culpeper Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the geology along the roads from Richmond to Culpeper by way of Fredericksburg. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Front Royal, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 13, [1840], I[srael] Slade, Front Royal, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the charms of springtime in the mountains and describing the geology observed by taking different routes between Front Royal and Strasburg via Middletown. 4 pp.
    - I[srael] Slade, Snickers Ferry, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 20, 1840, I[srael] Slade, Snickers Ferry, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of May 4 and explaining why he must vary from Rogers's directions with regard to collecting specimens around Strasburg; discussing the geology of the country between Front Royal, Winchester, and Snickers Ferry; describing a sulphur spring at Fort Valley; and commenting on the state of his own and Rogers's health. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - Israel Slade, Brocks Gap, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 23, [1840], Israel Slade, Brocks Gap, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the country around Hardy County, Virginia, including the Alleghany Mountain, the North Fork of the South Branch of the Potomac River, and various creeks. 4 pp.
    - George W. Boyd, Paris, Fauquier County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 24, 1840, George W. Boyd, Paris, Fauquier County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the geology of the country along his route from Culpeper County through Fairfax to Fredericksburg and from there through Warrenton to Paris; stating his intention to travel to Alexandria, then up the Potomac River through Harper's Ferry; noting that some instruments he wanted had not yet arrived at Fredericksburg; and relating an encounter with a Louisa Railroad train in which his horse lay down with fright. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 28, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, stating that the horse and buggy arranged for him by Rogers had proved unsatisfactory and that he had had to purchase new ones; asking for money for these purchases and for hiring a guide occasionally; and commenting on his health and the safe transportation of his boiling point thermometer. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Leesburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 7, 1840, George W. Boyd, Leesburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning Boyd's health; giving an account of the geology encountered on his way around Upperville, Middleburg, Aldie, Leesburg, and Dranesville; and describing the superior qualities of a turnpike paved with serpentine instead of the usual greenstone and quartz. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 13, 1840, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of June 4; saying that $500 had been deposited to his credit; and warning him of a forthcoming request for additional explanations and vouchers before his expense account could be approved. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Warrenton, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 14, 1840, George W. Boyd, Warrenton, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning his geological observations in Loudoun County and along the Potomac River near Harper's Ferry. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Milford, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 16, 1840, I[srael] Slade, Milford, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, complaining of being delayed by a lame horse and discussing the geology around Harper's Ferry and Shanandale Springs. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 4, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, acknowledging receipt of his letters of June 4 and 21; discussing a check enclosed in the first letter and his concern over Rogers's health; concluding that there are no valuable coal beds along the Ohio River from Fishing Creek to Carr's River; describing the geology of the same area; and mentioning that he had recovered Rogers's trunk. 4 pp.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Letart, Ohio, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 15, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Letart, Ohio, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, acknowledging receipt of his recent letter; explaining why he could not follow Rogers's instructions with regard to the trunk; and describing the distribution of coal along the Ohio River above and below Parkersburg. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Carr's or Kerr's Run, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 18, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Carr's or Kerr's Run, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, stating that he had determined that the center of the coal basin lay somewhere between Big Mill Creek and Letart Falls and describing the geology of the area; giving an account of his recent illnesses; and answering, mostly in the negative, Rogers's inquiry as to the abundance of "fair ladies and interesting damsels" in western Virginia. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Point Pleasant, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 25, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Point Pleasant, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, hoping to meet with him soon to discuss matters pertaining to the geology of that part of the state; discussing the Carr's Run coal seam and the record of a boring for a salt well at the mouth of Leading Creek; and informing him of his plans to proceed to Guyandotte and his hopes of receiving a letter there. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Buchanan, to W. B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 29, 1840, I[srael] Slade, Buchanan, to W. B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, asking for a new thermometer to replace one which had been broken; describing the geology of Botetourt and Alleghany counties around Short Hill, Purgatory Mountain, Craig's Creek, Rich Patch Mountain, and Covington; discussing the lack of adequate maps and the difficulty of mapping the region; and mentioning the geology of the James River Gap. 3 pp. with address leaf.